Welcome! In the last lecture, we successfully created a two key action that can only be
欢迎!在上一节课中，我们成功地创建了两个关键动作，只有
triggered when we are climbing. And now, with the callback function ready, in this lecture,
当我们在攀登时触发。现在，回调函数准备好了，在这节课中，
we are going to look at how we should trigger the hopping. So we've already taken care
我们将看看应该如何触发跳跃。所以我们已经注意到了
of this notifying climbing state, adding removing input mapping context, and next thing would
通知爬升状态，添加删除输入映射上下文，下一件事将是
be this request hopping. This one here should be triggered through player's input and our
就是这个要求的跳跃。这里的这个应该通过玩家的输入和我们的
custom movement component should take it from there and handle the hopping for us. So let's
自定义移动组件应该从那里获取它，并为我们处理跳跃。所以让我们
talk about this handle hopping. So the first thing that we need to figure out is the hopping
说说这个手柄跳跃吧。所以我们首先要弄清楚的是跳跃
direction. This action here should be entirely depending on our input. When the player triggers
方向。这里的操作应该完全取决于我们的输入。当玩家触发
hopping, if only the W key is down, then we should hop up. And if there's only the S key
跳跃，只要W键按下，我们就应该跳起来。如果只有S的钥匙
down, then we should hop down. But there are also cases where the player is moving to the
下来，然后我们应该跳下来。但也有一些情况下，球员将转移到
left and to the right through input. And more than this fall, our player can also move diagonally.
通过输入向左和向右。除了今年秋天，我们的球员还可以沿对角移动。
So top left, top right, there will be a total of eight cases that we need to handle, along
所以左上角，右上角，我们总共有八个案件需要处理，
with many other edge cases. And for simplicity's sake in here, I'm only going to allow our
与许多其他边缘情况。为了简单起见，我只允许我们的
character to hop up and down. And I'm going to categorize all the other scenarios as invalid
上下跳跃的角色。我会将所有其他场景归类为无效
input range. So in this lecture, we'll look at how we can figure out the hopping direction.
输入范围。因此，在这节课中，我们将看看如何找出跳跃的方向。
I'm first going to close my project, go back to my code. I'm going to go to this custom
我首先要结束我的项目，回到我的代码。我要去参加这个风俗
movement component.h and hide these regions. And under this public section below this toggle
移动组件.h并隐藏这些区域。在此切换下的公共部分下
climbing, I'm going to create a new function. I'm going to call this function request hopping.
攀登，我要创造一个新的功能。我将把这个函数称为RequestHopping。
And I'm going to create a function body and place the function at the bottom of this CPP file,
我将创建一个函数体，并将该函数放在此CPP文件的底部，
perhaps above this set motion board target. So place it in here. Then inside of our character
或许高于这一设定的动漫板目标。所以把它放在这里。然后在我们的角色内部
class, I'm going to call this function. So when this climb hop action started, I'm going to delete
类，我要调用这个函数。所以当这个爬升跳跃动作开始时，我将删除
this default function. I'm going to check if custom movement component is valid. If it is,
此默认功能。我要检查一下自定义移动组件是否有效。如果是的话，
I'm going to call the function request hopping. And next, our custom movement component should
我将调用函数RequestHopping。接下来，我们的自定义移动组件应该
take it from there. So go back to the CPP file. Here's what I like to do to figure out the
从那里开始吧。因此，返回到CPP文件。以下是我想要做的，以弄清楚
direction. So inside of the character movement component class, there's a function that we can
方向。因此，在角色移动组件类内部有一个函数，我们可以
use. It's called get last input vector. So with this function, we can know which is specific
使用。它被称为获取最后一个输入向量。所以有了这个函数，我们可以知道哪一个是特定的
movement action key is pressed, and we can act based on it. So to visualize this, I'm going to
按下移动操作键，我们就可以根据它来操作。因此，为了使这一点可视化，我将
print this value out. And same as our climbing velocity, I like to un-rotate this vector. So
将此值打印出来。和我们的爬升速度一样，我喜欢不旋转这个向量。所以
the value will always be consistent. So I'm going to use this ukismamath library and access the
该值将始终保持一致。所以我将使用这个ukismaath库并访问
function quad underscore un-rotate vector and pass in this updated component, get component quad. So
函数quad下划线取消旋转向量，并传入这个更新的组件，获取组件quad。所以
this is the cartonian and this is the vector that we want to un-rotate. So paste it in here.
这是Cartonian，这是我们想要取消旋转的矢量。所以把它贴在这里。
Then I'm going to store the return result of it inside of a local variable. So it's going to be
然后，我将把它的返回结果存储在一个局部变量中。所以这将会是
const f vector. I'm going to call it un-rotate it last input vector. Then I'm going to print this
常量f向量。我将它称为非旋转，最后一个输入向量。然后我要把这个打印出来
value out. So I'm going to select this variable. First, I'm going to use the function get safe
价值外溢。所以我要选择这个变量。首先，我将使用Get Safe函数
normal. Then I'm going to convert this value into a string. Next, I'm going to use the function debugged
很正常。然后，我将把这个值转换成一个字符串。接下来，我将使用已调试的函数
print and pass in this value. Since I want to call this function inside of tick, I'm going to also
打印并传入此值。由于我想在tick内部调用此函数，因此我还将
specify the color cyan and a value of one for this key. Then I'm going to copy these two lines,
为该关键点指定青色和值1。然后我要复制这两行，
go back to tick, paste them in here, and launch my editor back.
返回到Tick，粘贴到这里，然后启动我的编辑器。
Go inside of the editor, I'm going to click play. And I'm going to go to the surface here and press
进入编辑器内部，我要点击播放。我要到地面上去按下
F. So you can see when I'm moving up, the value for the z-axis will always be one.
所以你们可以看到，当我向上移动时，z轴的值总是1。
And when I'm moving to the left, the value will always be negative one for the y. No matter which
当我移到左边时，y的值总是为负1。无论是哪一个
surface I'm climbing, the value here will be consistent. And that's great. So this is the value
表面我在攀登，这里的价值将是一致的。这太棒了。这就是它的价值
that we're going to use to determine the hopping direction. So I'm going to go back to my code.
我们将用它来确定跳跃的方向。所以我要回到我的代码上来。
Now I'm going to delete these two lines and tick. We don't need to see them anymore.
现在我要删除这两行并打勾。我们不需要再见到他们了。
Then go back to my function request hopping. I'm going to delete this one. Since I'm only going to
然后返回到我的功能请求跳转。我要删除这一条。因为我只打算
allow our character to hop up and down, I'll need to rule out the other situations in here. And there
允许我们的角色上下跳跃，我需要排除这里的其他情况。还有那里
are plenty of ways for us to do that. And here I'm going to use the function dot product. So this
我们有很多方法可以做到这一点。在这里，我将使用函数点积。所以这就是
inside of this F vector dot product and the two vectors that I'm going to compare. The first one
在这个F向量点积和我将要比较的两个向量的内部。第一个
is this un-rotated last input vector. And the second one will be this F vector double column
是未旋转的最后一个输入向量。第二个是这个F向量双列
up vector. So I'm comparing our input vector with this up vector. And in case you forget the return
向上向量。所以我将我们的输入向量与这个向上向量进行比较。以防你忘了退货
result of a dot product, I'm going to store it inside of a local float. I'm going to call this
一个点积的结果，我将把它存储在一个局部浮点数中。我要把这个叫作
dot result. So if these two vectors, they are parallel, the value will be one. If they're the
点结果。所以如果这两个向量是平行的，那么这个值就是1。如果他们是
exact opposite, the value will be negative one. And in here, I'm going to directly print this value out.
恰好相反，该值将为负一。在这里，我将直接打印出这个值。
So it'll be debug print. And I'm going to say dot result and append a string in here. So it's going
所以它将是调试打印。我要说点结果，然后在这里附加一个字符串。所以它正在进行中
to be F string, sanitize float and pass in this dot result. Then I'm going to use an if check to
要成为F字符串，请清理浮动并传入此点结果。然后我将使用If检查来
check this dot result. So if this dot result is greater than 0.9f, then I'm going to print a message
检查这个点的结果。因此，如果这个点结果大于0.9F，那么我将打印一条消息
that says hop up. And else if this dot result is less than or equal to negative 0.9f,
上面写着跳起来。否则如果该点结果小于或等于负0.9F，
then I'm going to say this is hop down. Then in the else case, so if neither of these conditions
那我就说这是跳下来的。在Else的情况下，如果这两个条件都不是
is true, I'm going to print a message that says invalid input range. And that should be it.
为真，我将打印一条消息，指出输入范围无效。应该就是这样了。
These lines here to help us to figure out the hopping direction. All right, I'm going to quickly
这些线条帮助我们找出跳跃的方向。好的，我要很快地
save all then trigger live coding. All right, live coding succeeded. Let's test this. So I'm going to
全部保存，然后触发实时编码。好了，现场编码成功。让我们来测试一下这个。所以我要去
go to the surface, press F and I'm going to move up, then press space bar. Here it says hop up.
到表面，按F键，我要向上移动，然后按空格键。这上面写着跳上来。
Great. Move down, says hop down. And if I'm trying to move to the left, it says invalid input range,
太棒了。往下走，说往下跳。如果我试图移到左边，它会显示无效的输入范围，
move to the right and invalid input range. Great. Now I'm going to try to move to the top left.
移到右侧无效的输入范围。太棒了。现在我要试着移到左上角。
And here I'm having some incorrect result. It says hop up and that's not what I want.
在这里我得到了一些不正确的结果。上面说跳起来，这不是我想要的。
And I think I just know the reason for that. So I'm going to go back to my code.
我想我知道是什么原因了。所以我要回到我的代码上来。
So in here for this result, I forgot to add get safe normal. So this vector here is not normalized.
所以在这里，对于这个结果，我忘了添加Get Safe Normal。所以这里的这个向量没有被规格化。
That's why we are having the unexpected result. All right, quickly save all again,
这就是为什么我们会有意想不到的结果。好的，再次快速保存所有内容，
trigger live coding and go back to my project. I'm going to test this again.
触发实时编码并返回到我的项目。我要再测试一次。
So try to climb to the top left and this time it says invalid input range. Great. Top right,
所以试着爬到左上角，这一次它显示无效的输入范围。太棒了。右上角，
same thing. Bottom left, same thing. Bottom right and move to the right. And just like that,
同样的事情。左下角，一样的东西。右下角，然后向右移动。就像这样，
we have just filtered out the hopping direction from our input and we are almost there for our
我们刚刚从我们的输入中过滤掉了跳跃方向，我们几乎已经完成了
hopping. And I got some important notes for you. So the key function here is this get less input
跳跃。我有一些重要的笔记要给你。所以这里的关键功能是获得更少的输入
vector and make sure it's unrotated and normalized before you use it. Once you get
向量，并确保它在使用之前未旋转和规格化。一旦你得到了
hold of the information you need, you can use the dot product to tell if this is a valid input range
掌握所需信息后，可以使用点积来判断这是否是有效的输入范围
and we can use it to allow our character to hop up and down. Feel free to refer back to the video
我们可以用它来让我们的角色上下跳跃。请随时回看视频
if you need help and I'll see you in the next lecture.
如果你需要帮助，我会在下一节课上见到你。
[Music]
[音乐]